Register of the Frederic V. Malek papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Frederic V. Malek papers
1968-1977
84009
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (4.7 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and notes relating to domestic politics and administration of the federal government during the presidencies of Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Number of Containers:
Malek, Frederic V.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1937 December 22 Born, Oak Park, Illinois
1967-1969 Chairman, Triangle Corporation, Columbia, South Carolina
1969-1970 Deputy Under Secretary, Department of Health, Education and Welfare
1970-1973 Special Assistant to President Richard M. Nixon
1972 Deputy Director, Committee for the Re-election of the President
1973-1974 Deputy Director, Office of Management and Budget
1974-1975 Member, White House Domestic Council
1975- Vice President, Marriott Corporation
1978 Author, Washington's Hidden Tragedy: The Failure to Make Government Work
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; United States. Office of Management and Budget.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings. Arranged chronologically.
  - Clippings, 1971 April-1974 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1968-1978 (Boxes 1-3)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings with related correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - General. Memoranda, letters, and schedules, 1973 May-1975 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Background material. Notes, letters, clippings and speeches by William Simon, Arthur Burns and others, primarily relating to banking and economic policy, 1975 May-1976 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Assessment of Management Quality," Business Horizons, Reprint, 1968 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Analysis and Recommendations--The Food and Drug Administration Organizational Review," Food and Drug Cosmetic Law Journal, Printed article, 1970 Jan (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Master Plan for Merger Negotiations," Harvard Business Review, Reprint, 1970 Jan.-Feb (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Management Improvement in the Federal Government: An Inside View," Business Horizons, Reprint, 1971 Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Management Improvement in HEW: An Inside View," Management Review, Printed article, 1972 Jan (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview, Clipping, 1973 Feb. 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Speech, Typescript, 1973 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Speech, Typescript, 1973 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Speech, Typescript, 1973 Oct (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Speech, Typescript and a letter, 1973 Nov. 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "One That Got Away," New York Times, Clipping and a letter, 1973 Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Speech, Typescript, 1974 Feb. 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Testimony, U.S. Senate, Committee on Government Operations, Budgeting, Management and Expenditures Subcommittee, Typescript, 1974 Feb. 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Real Nixon Accomplishments Go Unheralded," Los Angeles Times, Typescript, letters and a clipping, 1974 Feb. 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Speech, Typescript and a letter, 1974 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Speech, Typescript and a letter, 1974 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Managing for Results in the Federal Government," Business Horizons, Reprint, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "The New Federalism--Making it Work," Typescript, ca. 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Speech, Typescript, ca. 1974 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Speeches, Notes, typescripts, letter, and clippings, 1974 April 2-10 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The New Federalism: The Kind of Change We Need," Chicago Tribune, Typescript and clipping, 1974 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "New Federalism: Giving Government Back to the People," Typescript, letters, and clippings, 1974 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Speech, Typescript and letters, 1974 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Speech, Typescript and memorandum, 1974 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "The Federal Dollars in New Federalism," Typescript, letters and a flyer, 1974 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "The Development of Public Executives--Neglect and Reform," Public Administration Review, Reprint, 1974 May-June (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter to the Editor, Wall Street Journal, Typescript and clipping, 1974 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Speech, Typescript, 1974 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Interview, Notes and a draft statement, ca. 1974 Aug (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Reflections on Five and One Half Years with President Nixon," Typescript and a letter, 1974 Aug (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "The New Federalism," Typescript and a letter, 1974 Aug (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "The Art and Politics of Public Management," Notes, a letter and other miscellaneous materials relating to a Harvard University study group, 1976 April (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Washington's Hidden Tragedy: The Failure to Make Government Work, 1978
    - General
      - Background material (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence and comments. NOTE: Specific chapter comments are with those chapters (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Outlines and notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chapters. Typescripts, notes, letters and comments, clippings, printed articles and other background materials
      - 1-4 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
      - 5-11 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
- DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, EDUCATION AND WELFARE FILE, 1969-1976 (Box 4)
  Speech transcript, letters, reports, appointment book, clippings, printed articles, procedural manual, charts, memoranda, and agenda. Primarily relates to management planning within the agency. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - General. Speech transcript, a photocopy of a letter from Elliot Richardson to Barry Goldwater, and a brief summary of authorizing legislation, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Appointment book, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Clippings and printed articles, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Management planning
    - General. Charts, reports, agenda and memoranda, 1969 Nov.-1971 Oct (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reports and procedural manuals. Includes cover memoranda and reports written by Frederic Malek for H.R. Haldeman and others, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
- WHITE HOUSE FILE, 1969-1977 (Boxes 4-7)
  Pamphlet, press releases, charts, letters, appointment books, clippings, minutes, reports, memoranda, printed articles, notes, and lists. Relates to the organization of the Executive Branch, personnel, and high-level appointments in the Nixon Administration. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - General. Pamphlet of statements by Richard Nixon, charts entitled "Legislative Infringements or Limitations on the Executive," press releases, and a letter of reply to Lyndon B. Johnson, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Appointment books, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Clippings, 1970 Nov.-1976 Feb (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cabinet meetings. Minutes, 1971 Nov.-1974 March (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Information leaks. Primarily monthly progress reports relating to an improper disclosure directive, 1971 June-1972 June (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Magruder, Jeb S. Memoranda relating to job placement, 1972 Dec (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Organization and reorganization of the Executive branch. SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF MANAGEMENT AND BUDGET FILE/Reorganization
    - General. Press releases, clippings, reports, memoranda, letter, and printed articles, 1970 Sept.-1977 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Transition (post-1972 election). Memoranda and reports relating to transition plans; includes a memorandum from Richard Nixon to H.R. Haldeman relating to the CIA, 1971 Oct.-1973 Feb (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - White House staff. Reports, notes, charts, printed article, and memoranda relating primarily to White House personnel, legal services, and public relations functions, 1971 Jan.-1973 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Recruiting and placement
    - General
      - General. Relates to vacancies and personnel searches
        - Memoranda, 1970 Oct.-1972 Dec (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Notes. Primarily meetings with other White House staff members and advisors, 1970 Sept.-1972 May (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Consultants. Proposals and notes, ca. 1970 Oct (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Sources. Memorandum from H.R. Haldeman to Richard Nixon, 1970 Nov (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - White House Task Force on Executive Manpower. List and handbook, 1970 Nov (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ambassadors. Lists, memoranda, letters, and a press release, 1971 Oct.-1974 June (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Departments
      - General. Memoranda and notes primarily relating to Cabinet-level appointments, 1972 Sept.-1973 Jan (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Agriculture Department. Memoranda, 1971 Oct.-Nov (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Commerce Department. Memoranda and a schedule, 1971 Dec.-1974 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Defense Department. Memoranda, 1971 April-1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Health, Education and Welfare Department. Memoranda, 1970 Dec.-1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Housing and Urban Development Department. Memoranda, 1972 Dec.-1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Interior Department. List and memoranda, 1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Justice Department. Memoranda, 1971 Dec.-1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Labor Department. Memoranda, 1971 July-1972 Dec (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - State Department. Memoranda, 1971 April-1972 March (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Transportation Department. Memoranda, 1972 Nov.-1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Treasury Department. Memoranda, clipping and a letter, 1970 Dec.-1974 June (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Independent agencies and regulatory commissions. Memoranda, letter, notes, a clipping, and biographies. Includes material relating to the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, the Securities and Exchange Commission, ACTION, the Atomic Energy Commission, the Federal Reserve Board, and others; also includes material relating to a U.S. Senate symposium on regulatory agency appointments, 1971 Oct.-1976 Sept (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Schorr, Daniel. Clippings, press release, memoranda, notes and letters from Sen. Sam Ervin, Jr., 1971 Nov.-1972 Jan (Box 7, Folder 13)
- COMMITTEE FOR THE RE-ELECTION OF THE PRESIDENT FILE, 1971-1974 (Box 7)
  Clippings, radio transcript, correspondence, memoranda, reports, pamphlets, a deposition and other legal materials. Primarily relates to informal recommendations on whether or not various organizations should receive grant funding. Arranged alphabetically by form.
  - Clippings. Includes a transcript of a new report by Walter Cronkite for CBS radio, 1973 Dec.-1974 June (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence. Notes and correspondence with Senators Sam Ervin, Jr., Robert Byrd, Herman Talmadge, Mike Mansfield and Howard Baker, Jr., relating to specific projects, 1973 Jan.-Aug (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Memoranda
    - General. Collected memoranda and a short report entitled "Administration Efforts in Support of the Re-election.", 1971 July-1972 June (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Memoranda from Frederic Malek to H.R. Haldeman and others, relating primarily to convention planning, press and public relations, and the re-direction of the White House staff to support the re-election of Richard Nixon, 1971 Sept.-1972 Dec (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Publications. Republican National Committee, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Report. "Use of the Incumbency-Reponsiveness Program", with memoranda analyzing the report, ca. 1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Testimony. Deposition by Frederic Malek, letters and miscellaneous legal material, 1973 July-1974 March (Box 8, Folder 2)
- OFFICE OF MANAGEMENT AND BUDGET FILE, 1970-1977 (Boxes 8-11)
  Clippings, correspondence, appointment book, reports, speeches, memoranda, printed articles, press releases, notes, budgets, agenda, and a pamphlet. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General. Clippings, letter, interview outline, appointment book, and reports, 1973 Jan.-1975 Sept (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
  - Budgets
    - General. Clippings, primarily relating to the Carter Administration, 1973 Sept.-1977 Jan (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Economic analyses. Speech, proposals, and memoranda relating to wage-price controls and general economic policy, 1974 Jan.-July (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - FY 1974. Fact sheet, report, and memoranda, 1973 Feb.-1974 Feb (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - FY, 1975
      - Memoranda, 1973 Feb.-1974 June (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
      - Public relations material. Press releases, statements by Richard Nixon and Frederic Malek, charts, and notes for presentations, primarily to various Congressional committees, 1973 Sept.-1974 April (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Reviews. Director's review of HEW budget and materials for a presidential review of energy, science and natural resources agencies, ca. 1973 Nov (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - FY Statement, report, press release and charts, 1975, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Domestic policy
    - General. Memoranda and proposals, 1973 May-Aug (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - White House Domestic Council. Memoranda, ca. 1973 Jan.-1974 July (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Management
    - General. Memoranda, agenda, report, and correspondence with Sen. Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1970 Dec.-1976 Aug (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Management by Objectives program. Reports, memoranda, letters, agency proposals, presidential objectives, agenda, and printed articles, 1972-1975 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Personnel
    - General. Memoranda, pamphlet, and notes, 1970 Aug.-1975 Dec (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Federal Executive Development Program. Memoranda and reports, 1974 Jan.-1976 Nov (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - President's Commission on Personnel Interchange. Letter, agenda and background materials for meetings, memoranda, and a pamphlet, 1974 May-July (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Reorganization
    - General. Memoranda, proposals, press releases and notes, SEE ALSO: WHITE HOUSE FILE/Reorganization, 1972 Nov.-1973 Jan (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Office of Management and Budget. Proposals, letter, printed articles, meeting notes, charts, and memoranda, 1972 Dec.-1974 Dec (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Undersecretaries group. Memoranda, meeting reports and notes; includes material relating to conferences at Camp David, 1973 Feb.-1974 July (Box 11, Folder 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1973-1976 (Box 11)
  Pamphlets, letters, charts, reports, notes, printed articles, and clippings relating to other government departments. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Commerce Department. Pamphlets relating to department objectives and management conferences, 1973 June-1974 June (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Drug Enforcement Administration. Notes, printed article, clipping, statement, a letter and a report, 1973 March-1976 Nov (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Housing and Urban Development Department. Reports, charts and letters, including a photocopy of a letter from Gerald Ford, 1974 Sept.-1976 Nov (Box 11, Folder 5)
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1972-1973
  - Photographs, 1972-1973
    3 prints and one proof sheet of a swearing-in ceremony, with Frank Zarb, Frederic Malek, and others; one print and one proof sheet of Frederick Malek.
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1973
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Available as PDF files. The PDF files are page images, so full-text search is not possible. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - Record released in 2010, 1973